If the release cadence of Angular versions
stays as it is, I think we'll see each other
here every 6 months, Jorge, right? The truth is yes,
we are doing well, right? I don't even know how many we've done.
How many has it been? Years of this already. I think it's
17, so if we do a little arithmetic there,
I think it's almost 3 years in this, giving
a few updates on what's coming,
what is not coming as well, what the
expectations are, how to prepare for the new
versions, what to keep in mind a few days before or,
as happened to us once, a month before the release of
the version, what to keep in mind to approach
the major version in a way that doesn't surprise us,
that doesn't take us by storm. Yes, yes.
How time flies! Eh, though I must say something,
the one from that month was my fault, so
I'll take responsibility as always. Yes,
that's in one of the episodes of the
many we've already recorded. You are competing with
Eduardo Roth in the number of episodes we
have here on Angularidades. I think this is
like your eighth episode. So I am
immensely grateful to have you
once more around here, and we'll keep incrementing the for loop
for what lies ahead. If Angular
keeps making these biannual releases. Yes,
yes, it's been a while, but well, happy,
happy again to be here, so I'm
thrilled, you know. Great. And so,
Jorge, if you had to describe what's coming
now, this week, possibly on Wednesday,
what word, what term would you use
to describe Angular 22?
You know, well, I don't know, at least in Argentina,
because I was going to say a phrase like
and I was going to throw it out as if everyone was
the same, but eh here in Argentina they usually say
when something is lacking, right? That it lacks maturity,
that it's green. And I think it stops being green,
right? It goes back to not being green,
which is not the first time, right? I mean,
we've gone through several stages, but I think
that's it, right? I mean, it has reached a maturity and a
fairly strong stability. I think those are the
words I would have: stability, maturity.
And I agree with you, this concept of Modern
Angular that came after the Renaissance,
which coincided with the first episode we recorded
together about the anticipation of what was coming
in v17, I think that yes, this is the stable
version, the version that comes to land what
has to do with Signal Forms, resources,
and a series of elements there that were, well,
there are still a few hanging for 23,
for 24, but now using modern Angular
is not something that is cutting-edge, it's not
pioneering, it's not extremely experimental or
however it might be seen in the corporate world.
Everything that already has to do with control flow,
with standalone or autonomous components, with
this whole signal graph system, is no longer
something unknown, it's not something that will take
by surprise any developer or any
person who is behind a technical decision
to advance the framework to use the
new architectural patterns. The truth is that
yes, I mean, clearly we can finally say again
that we returned to stability, that there is
nothing new to learn and that I can use everything,
right? Totally. And well, as we always do, in
case someone hasn't seen any of
the episodes where we had the chance
to see you, let me introduce you to those
people who still don't know you. By your accent,
it's clear that you are from Argentina, specifically from
Buenos Aires. You are a speaker, technical writer,
and instructor of several courses
related to JavaScript and web performance
in general. You have the distinction of Google
Developer Expert in three categories: the category
of Web Technologies, Firebase, and obviously
Angular. Here we are again. If you didn't
know me, you can go 150 episodes back,
which I think was my first time. We have many
episodes. I already feel like a co-host, that's all
I'm going to say. But well, thanks again
for the invitation. Sure, thank you very much,
grateful, obviously, for every moment
that we can share together. So,
what is it that doesn't change in 22 to
create a prelude of what's coming with this new
version? We had expected for a while,
meaning specifically two versions ago,
when they deprecated all these structural
directives of *ngIf, *ngFor
and *ngSwitch in favor of the new control
flow structure: @if, @for, @switch. We had expected that
based on the lifecycle of framework features,
they would be removed in two versions.
But from an architectural point of view,
what happened with the team? What
was the decision made to continue
extending the lifespan of these directives?
Ah, I don't know if you remember, but I was
against these directives to start with,
I want to say. And then I was very in favor
because not only at the architecture level, but at
the performance level, I mean, it has many benefits,
many benefits. I think what happens is that
today many people don't want to break what's
old, and for maintainability and CI/CD and there are so many
things not to break that I don't even know. I mean, it's
like: it's deprecated, but I'll give you a little more
time. We know that Angular is very corporate today,
meaning that many large corporations use
Angular and that makes it a reality. They move
very differently. I don't even know if they can use AI,
right? So I think it's basic, right? For
me, I mean, beyond everything you can say,
there is a reality, which is that not everyone is
on the latest version of Angular, not even close.
So, many times you want to update the
version, but your code is a bit legacy,
in quotes. So, you have no choice
but to update for security reasons,
but then you can't use this because you have to
use that. So, I think there is an issue there,
right? I mean, it's like: I'm giving you a little more
time. And the framework is also cleaning itself up,
right? Eh, by marking it deprecated,
it indicates that we should start
devising a series of directives,
guidelines rather, that allow us to mature
the codebase towards the direction that Angular
is taking. And for example, in the
case of this cleanup, now with v22 the
support for Shadow DOM selectors is removed,
which are already considered legacy and,
consequently, CSS polyfills. Remember
that file that was huge about
10 or approximately 5 years ago? There are still
polyfills internally that are not exposed to
us as developers in
our codebase, the part we can control,
but there are a lot
of conditional polyfills in there, in the
internals of the framework, that are gradually being
cleaned up, specifically those old ones like /deep/ or
::shadow and a series of other elements that
were rarely used and were replaced
by other much more modern conventions.
Look, to give you an idea, to give you
an idea of what we are going to talk about polyfills,
on my channel there are 257 videos. Video number one,
meaning the first video I uploaded is about polyfills
in AngularJS. Wow! What year was that? That
video is from November 29, 2013. 2013.
And if you could look back in
time, what would you say to Jorge,
to stop worrying a bit about polyfills,
that in a decade things would be better regarding
the standardization of a series of
conventions in the modern web or what? No,
I think I would have never believed that still
frameworks had to use polyfills
hidden internally. I wouldn't have
believed that if you ask me. Eh, still to give,
as you said, right?, to give extended
support, in quotes, right?, beyond LTS,
to corporations that are still behind
this new mechanism they are
implementing. They help with schematics,
they help with this same lifecycle process,
but even so, resistance to change is deep.
Yes. And not only resistance to change,
right? I mean, always, I mean, it's like, well,
maturation-wise when you start working more
and more, you realize that many
times, if you tell the person above you
(doesn't matter, even if you are the CTO, you have the
CEO above you), between a feature or changing all
the *ngIf directives, they are going to look at you and say:
"Why are you asking me? Do the feature because
I have to go out and sell, or for this or for
that." It's not like the latest is always first, and
I think I always say it, right?: it's like the return
on investment is for us. Today,
computers are fast, and this and that, and
phones, right? So, unfortunately, it's always
left for last, this kind of thing, because
there are other priorities. It's just that planning technical debt
is quite challenging for
any team, specifically institutions
that have an extremely large codebase,
systems that were created
a decade ago with a different way of doing things.
But well, the Angular system,
the framework itself, cleans itself up a bit.
For example, this TypeScript thing is no longer going to be
compatible with versions prior to 6.0.
Yes, it's quite rare that someone would do a
little cherry-picking with dependencies and
try to force 22 to work with 5.
Because in the end, when you run these update
schematics, the framework automatically
makes all the adjustments for developers,
with direct and transitive dependencies,
so there is little to worry about
with these kinds of mechanisms, but well,
the framework itself also completely removes
APIs that were already obsolete, like the
ComponentFactoryResolver, the
ComponentFactory, remember that? The part in
the router to match routes now requires
mandatorily the currentSnapshot parameter.
I think it's good, I mean, we have to move forward,
sometimes we have to force it because otherwise it's impossible. I mean,
the problem is always, right? If Angular keeps
giving support to such old versions, the codebase of
Angular becomes huge and there are a lot of
ifs in the middle, so to speak, or it cuts.
They did it with RxJS, right? Do you remember when it was
all deprecated, when they migrated the RxJS version,
which was impossible to migrate and everything was deprecated
and your code was full of deprecation warnings? That was
from 5 to 6 of RxJS. Exactly. It was
very hard. I mean, you literally had to use
a compat package, because otherwise it gave you deprecated warnings
everywhere, and the compat was a compatibility package that
internally bridged one import and the other.
It was terrible. But that's why,
that's why I think we talk about maturity and I think
the team itself matured, like saying: "Well,
I mean, there is a clear direction, there are clear
things, and these are it." Even having very clear
what the priorities are on the roadmap. Is
the decision of the team clear
to have three specific priorities? Number
one: to continue offering an experience
that is at the level of modernity regarding
everything related to the development of
AI, of being engineers who can use the
framework of the future, not the framework of before
all the explosion of Agentic Engineering, of working
with a series of structures that facilitate
the inclusion of these tools
within the framework. Second: developer
experience, and third, of course,
to keep the framework performance
even better, because do you remember that about the
convergence with the Wiz framework, which is the
internal framework that had already been announced
interoperably, meaning, YouTube
started using signals? Yes. Let's see,
about these three points. The first is, I already
told you not long ago, we were together, eh,
not together on a call, but together in person.
The language itself ends up being a commodity,
so the better integrated it is, the more it will
be chosen. I mean, if you have to choose something
new or if you have to think about maintainability
or if you have to think about a migration. Therefore,
Angular has to mature that, no matter what.
In fact, the other day I was reading that
Google gives unlimited Gemini to its employees.
So, if Gemini doesn't work well with Angular,
we are in trouble. Exactly. Which is the foundation,
right? The basics, so to speak. So, all those
tooling features have to be very well put together. So, for me, I mean,
the three pillars of Angular are very
well thought out. Developer experience, because we
already know that AI is something that boosts you, not something
that replaces you. So, the necessity is absolute,
performance and also everything that comes with
retrocompatibility, you need it because not
everyone can update to the latest all the
time, or sometimes it's better to fix a bug
or a feature because it gives a higher ROI than
doing a code update. So, developer experience,
and so if you make it good and comfortable for people, they will
want to keep working because everything works on the
first try, not after 15 questions if
you manage the AI well. Topic aside. Second: if your
app takes too long and is very heavy, people won't
want to use it or they will complain or need more
RAM, and we already know how this goes. Today, people
use more Chrome tabs than applications on the
computer, right? I mean. And the third is the
developer experience. We already know we are 10x Engineers,
we are now. It's like AI gave us that power,
right? Like if a radio-active Spider-Man bit you,
we have that power. The issue is how we carry it,
if we carry it well or carry it bad. And there
our experience has a lot to do with
how we develop to be able to choose one
thing or the other, because AI doesn't do everything,
everything depends on us. AI is the executor. That's
why I talked about commodities, right? Of languages or
technology as a commodity. So it is:
Where are you most comfortable? You are most comfortable with
Angular. The AI is comfortable with Angular. But you
feel comfortable with AI with Angular,
you feel comfortable with the final delivery and the
performance it has, and for me that goes hand in
hand, right? I mean, and that is my mindset today
as well. And these principles, meaning
these priorities that the framework has, are not
mutually exclusive. We see in the case of Signal
Forms the classic example that they all go
hand in hand, because promoting the Signal Forms
API to stable allows for better form handling,
it allows us to remove the dilemma of whether
to use Reactive Forms with RxJS or use
Template-Driven Forms, even if there are purists in
each of the specific categories of making
forms. Here we have the third one that already comes
to solve a series of elements that allows for
better granular control of everything related to the
reactive mechanism, lower cost in syncing the
views with the state of the form.
It's a win-win for everyone,
from the Angular team to the developer
who uses this new form mechanism.
I think it's the first time Angular has a decent
form mechanism, let's say, because it was always
missing something. Since we used Reactive, we didn't want
to be completely in RxJS, so it wasn't at 100%.
If you used this one, no, it was like there was always
a 'but', right? It was like: "I like this but this",
"I like this but this", "I like this but this". In Signals, in
the Signal Forms, I haven't found the 'but' yet.
Well, you have to migrate, I mean, putting aside the work,
I say, what is the 'but' for not using it? Not using it
means it will be completely out of line with what is
considered a well-performing application, for apps
to work fast, in an efficient way, so you can build
a form without surprises, without too much boilerplate,
without a lot of code that then you have to maintain,
along with test harnesses and schematics,
that entire ecosystem is capable of executing
the initial idea you had, which basically is taking
the input from a series of elements the end user fills
out and passing them to the server. Period.
A form, no need to complicate it further. Exactly. And well,
returning to the RxJS topic, now with the
integration of the debounce rule,
natively in Signal Forms, in Angular 22 the
need to rely is eliminated,
rely on debounceTime or other resources we
had to delay validations,
avoiding unnecessary requests on every, you know,
keypress, on every action, and having a control
that is much more direct and oriented to the
signal graph solving all these internal reactive
mechanisms. Yes, it's over, it's over, it's over.
RxJS, yes, almost, almost. I think there
are still some internal elements in the framework that
depend on RxJS, but gradually, as we get closer to
v24, to Angular v25, maybe that RxJS dependency
we have every time we install Angular will be
completely eliminated, making it optional.
If one wants to continue the RxJS path towards
the version, maybe if v8 comes out at some point
in the future (I don't know if it will), but let it be a
decision of the architect or developer, an
architectural decision precisely, not something that
forces us to have the framework in the dependencies
list and thus increase the bundle size of the app,
making it render slower on the browser side
because you are injecting more JavaScript, you are
doing more rendering, and that is what the modern
Angular mechanisms are all about, to guarantee that
the app is more efficient when built and deployed
later in a browser. Yes, to be honest,
it gives me a bit of nostalgia, but at the same time
you realize that you moved forward, right? I mean,
it was about time. Period. I think it's like,
it's done, we already knew it. In fact, RxJS itself
is deprecating, in quotes, right? I mean, I don't
want to say it wrong, but before RxJS flew, I mean,
ReactiveX was a whole movement, but well, you have to
accept it, right? Just as we abandoned jQuery,
AngularJS, and so on, right? Let's accept
that it's time to leave RxJS behind and we must move
to Signals, which is better and works, and all
the benefits we have, right? And as I
mentioned in one of the previous chapters, I think
it was in one of the conversations I had with
Eduardo, just because a technology worked
well for its time doesn't mean we
have to keep carrying that technology with us
and vice versa. If technology is now
becoming obsolete, it doesn't mean
the technology has become bad. The technology,
meaning, it fulfilled its purpose in the era in
which it was established, and we must appreciate that it
existed, that RxJS was part of the Angular framework
because it allowed, with its pros and cons,
to evolve in a way that led to Angular
being what it is today. Yes, it's like complaining, I don't know,
about a Game Boy or a PlayStation 1. It's like, how
are you going to complain? It was spectacular, but well,
yes, that's reality. I think that not
accepting that RxJS, I mean, even though I built
a lot, meaning I built pure RxJS and so on, is
a bit about maturing, right? And we are talking
about the framework maturing and everything we
have been saying, and I think we've been saying it
for a long time, right? It's like: it's there and it works,
we have to mature. And Jorge, with this
self-cleaning, do you remember? The removal of
a series of obsolete selectors that had to
do with Shadow DOM, but at the same time it's not
that Shadow DOM is something of the past in Angular,
but that it is being restructured, it is being taken
to a higher capacity, everything related
to this type of mechanism. For example, it
shows now that in 22 the support is incorporated,
official support now, thankfully, to be able to start,
meaning bootstrapping Angular applications
directly inside a shadow root.
So that's massive for any architecture
that uses micro-frontends or Web Components that
go towards that level of encapsulation.
Look, I'm not a fan of micro-frontends, I want
to say it. Web Components, I'm like,
there, and speaking of that, they have
a giant shell with two hundred apps, right? I mean,
something real, but I think we have to understand
how it moves, right? I mean, and to speak of it
in an easy way, Gmail, which we all know
and use all the time,
every time you click 'New' you get a
component that is rendered at that moment,
and not only is it rendered at that moment,
but that component can be a technology that
has nothing to do with the one you are using
in the browser, right? Which in the end is
a Web Component and which, I say, has a structure
and an infrastructure. For me that is for
very large tools and a whole discussion.
Again, they had to do it, it was part
of the maturation and, second, even though one
might not like it, which is a separate issue, right?
Or if it's not useful to me, it doesn't mean
it is not needed, and that's what we were talking about, right?
If you don't have all this, today you are kind of
out of the game. So for me, that they removed
everything related to Shadow DOM, well, all
the CSS polyfills and everything they committed, and
on top of that, that now in the bootstrap you can do a
shadow root, it's like it makes me happy. That's the
word. It's that it's giving the possibility
to people who want to incorporate verticals,
meaning, not making a micro-frontend to represent
a button or represent a small element on the
screen, because that would be like too much,
it has no purpose, it's an anti-pattern,
but when it comes architecturally to being able
to deploy, to allow teams to
independently compile and deploy without having
to affect the core of the main business or the
app. I understand, for example,
that Amazon doesn't use Angular, but they use
micro-frontends in that architecture, that architectural
pattern to solve that,
the deployment of elements that are large,
of functionalities, in a way that they are
independent of the rest of the teams. And this
of Angular allowing that bootstrapping at the level of
shadow root, I don't use it, but I know there are people
who will appreciate this type of change in 22.
And in the end, it's what we say, right? If you don't
have it, you're out. So, a bit is, eh,
maybe for apps of a certain size or needs
or scale, they are not necessary,
but if you want another scale, other needs or
whatever, you have to have it. So it is a bit
like that, right? It's having the possibility of not doing an
A/B testing, uploading everything or putting a feature flag that
in reality, I don't have this, I upload it, Angular
already routes it because now it has the shadow root,
starts the bootstrapping, boom, boom, boom, boom, you
have it, you have it, you want to use it, you don't want to use it,
that's another thing, but you have it. Sure. And for
that is this framework, to give you the solution
if you need to use it, correct? And by the way,
something we will all appreciate, I think,
well, there are cases, of course, specific ones
that might fall out of the rule, but something
that lands not as experimental and as developer
preview, but directly as stable, is the
new @Service decorator, the service class, which comes to
mark a drastic change when it comes to allowing
not only developer experience, but also
better efficiency in the framework, because you remember
this has been there since the beginning of Angular,
meaning @Injectable to be able to provide
services. But, how much boilerplate?
How much overhead did
that type of decorator have? Because it had to allow
for separate classes, separate values,
constructor injections, and all that took
code, took a series of elements there in the
internals of the framework, and what we need
is to put a singleton in the root and period. We don't
need more than that, and what do you think of this
move? Honestly, it's about appreciation,
I mean, anything that means less boilerplate, and I'll
say it clearly, is better for many
things, and we always talk about it, right? At first
we wrote it, then it was like pressing tab,
then this, then that, but today
if we go to the tokens model, so to speak,
which gives all that unnecessary boilerplate,
it was a lot of things, meaning it consumes tokens,
right? If you move that, if you take it to the
developer experience,
the DX, it's like: why do I have to do all
this? @Service, well, like we had, I mean,
the injectable, right? The @Injectable
that you put everywhere all the time,
right? And you already knew that, and you learned it by
heart, it was like the @Component, I remember
the @Component by heart from Angular 2 and it was what
you wrote. So it's like: remove things from me,
don't give me, I mean, give me, but by removing. I think
that's a good developer experience. And here
with this dependency it's like the dependency injection
with @Service, you are giving me, it was already there,
but well, you are giving me something by removing
the whole problem from me because one wants
a framework for that. So, personally,
10 out of 10, and possibly a schematic comes along
that checks, I say, if you are not using
resources to do an injection in
constructor or to use a much more
specific prototyping, the replacement will be very easy to
achieve, and possibly it is the direction in which
we want to continue when it comes to
dependency injection, because in the end what
you do is remove the useClass, the useValue,
I mean, if you are not using it, it makes no sense
to have to continue with the @Injectable decorator.
The @Injectable decorator comes with a
greater overhead, meaning you are putting a lot
more information in the JavaScript, which
eventually will be part of the Angular runtime in
a browser. If you don't use it, remove it. Inject that
as singleton, inject it directly in the root
just like it is in the style guides it should
be, as documented in the style guide. And of
course, always do yourself the favor of not declaring
in the component what is not going to be directly
transmitted to the view. Any element that
could be, with your Cuban voice, all good,
I want you to threaten people who do that, to
say that you're going to search for them at home because
they can't do that. Please, it's like: enough.
Having a monolith component of 100 lines of
code is super easy today to extract
and tell the artificial intelligence, and to
have your rules very clear in a markdown file
or maybe in a script, in an agent you
have destined for that. Very precisely tell it
the single responsibility principle. What
can be handled by services, for services,
what will allow the flow between the state and
the view in the component and in the template,
meaning in the final template, only what
has to do with the template, because I've
seen everything, I've even seen things that should
go in the service in the template, I imagine,
it's terrible. I've seen things in services that
are trying to touch the DOM directly.
I will tell you. A story of
30 seconds. A company contacts me saying
that their developer couldn't test the app
because it didn't run on their computer, if I could
fix it. I went, he told me the path that didn't run,
right? I mean, very fast, eh? Imagine what
it was. I open the file, it had 5700 lines.
There was an entire module, not an NgModule, but a complete component, right? The @Component
written completely in a single component. Templates, ifs, I mean, everything in there. When I say everything
is everything. What I did was split it into I think
it was six or seven different components. A shell,
right? A container component. I gave it back to him and
it started working for him. So I say,
it's just that if you do that, it's more manageable, the
app can be maintained better, you can
incorporate better unit tests, basically
the end result is nice. Also, imagine.
I remember that a function more or less like that,
instead of looking for it globally, you look for it only in
that file. It was crazy. Eh, it took days eh
to do this, but to give you an idea of
the things you can do. There is the
problem, right? I mean, Angular is a framework
that gives you very clear structures, but in the end
if you want to do something ugly, you can.
do. Sure. So dependency injection, using
@Service instead of @Injectable, as long
as you don't have an extreme use case in which
you need to continue. Even if you do,
try to study why you are doing it
that way and simplify your life,
simplify the life of everyone who
later will review that code so they
don't have to go through the same things you did
to make those kinds of structures. Sure,
so that good practices are the rule and not
the exception. Let's say the same. And well,
now with 22, also speaking of dependency
injection, comes the function to inject
dependencies asynchronously. Therefore,
any architecture that will benefit
from lazy loading with dependency injection, this
will change quite a bit the way we
are facing injecting inside
an Angular component or inside
a directive anything we have
declared in a service. I like it a lot,
I mean, I'm going to compare it to NgIf to
make it more humanly visible, right? NgIf,
what did it do? Everything inside that
block didn't execute, didn't render,
nothing. It was literally commenting something above
and commenting something below and nothing appeared
in the middle. And when that if became true,
it rendered. Right, so you didn't consume memory,
you didn't consume rendering. Well, first of all
everything we know we need with the
@if. This is almost the same. Like until I
need that dependency, I'm not going to inject it.
Period, because you might never need it.
It's what I always say, right? There might be something
that is an exception to the rule of what
you always do on that screen, to say something,
in that component, that needs a dependency,
and what happens? You always inject it. So this,
again, I mean, I'm very happy with
this release of Angular, very happy, very happy
likewise. Even it's not only about
the changes they've made now with the
signals, with the stabilization of resources,
meaning resources, but they are also touching
several areas, among them routing.
For example, now they allow to configure natively
something that anyone who had used the component
input binding in a route and you don't have the input,
meaning it doesn't match any of the inputs you
have in the component, you then had to write logic
to be able to give a solution to the end user so it wouldn't
get complicated if this happened. So now the
new function they incorporate, unmatchedInputBehavior,
in the router allows deciding what occurs when the URL
tries to pass properties
that don't exist there in those component inputs.
Honestly, I didn't look at it deeply, but from what you
say, it's like, how many times have we had the
error screen? Or this data doesn't appear, right?
We have no idea and it gives an error and, I mean, honestly, it seems interesting, I mean, I want to look into it more.
And there is another big headache that is solved
in the router, changing the behavior
by default of the parameter inheritance strategy
to always happen. Therefore,
now children automatically inherit all the parameters
of the parent routes without there being an
additional configuration, an extra configuration
that one has to incorporate.
Great. What a beautiful, what a beautiful moment to be
a developer. That's all I'm going to say.
How much we have suffered! How much we have suffered!
Remember that before one had to incorporate
so much code, and not only
ow we have the framework doing it,
but also the AI adjusting and allowing
to read in the skills what exists? And
you go 10x, even a bit beyond the speed
normally expected for
a developer previously. Yes, yes. The
truth is that between MCPs, eh,
the learning of the AI itself on the framework and
these things, eh, it's like it's going to sound a bit cliché,
but I say, it's hard not to go fast in the good
sense, fast and well, I don't mean making an
app in 30 seconds, don't get me wrong,
making the copy of Word and all that. I mean that today
a feature or an improvement or an update of
this style ends up making a migration easy.
It was already easier with everything the Angular team
was doing with schematics and so on,
right? Because schematics are born a bit to make
our lives easier, but with all this plus
what there is, it's like hard not to go at a nicer
pace, right? I mean, it makes you want to,
right? I don't know if you get into that mood,
as I call it, of wanting to push, wanting to push
and wanting to push, and suddenly time flies
like in the old days when you were developing.
That is happening to me. Yes, that is something
we are all experiencing, like returning to the
beginnings of going directly with an idea,
implementing it, that reward. And Jorge, with this
stabilization of HTTP Resource, HTTP Resource
is with the underlying HttpClient underneath
the facade, and there are some changes there we can
see in the changelog of the versions that have come out
as candidates before 22.0.0.
For example, there is this progress monitoring a bit
more granular. Previously we only had the
original reportProgress configuration,
but now you can incorporate the option of uploadProgress
or report download progress.
So in case we have some UI with a progress bar indicating
where a download or upload is, we already have
the facility to do it. Even
more so with the resource API being stable.
In fact, I'll tell you, I remember
I did uploads with pure JavaScript
to handle the upload percentage well,
or using fetch directly and bypassing the
HttpClient completely. Sure, before
fetch, a bit older. How was it? With XHR.
Yes, XMLHttpRequest. Exactly, because it was the
only way to get all the necessary data to
understand the upload really. So
we used that, bypassing Angular completely because it
was the way to do it right. I mean,
if you just wanted to upload it, eh, you could go there.
If you wanted to have a lot of parameters,
times, put, well, the typical stuff, you know?
When you upload it shows remaining time, percentage,
at what speed you are uploading or downloading.
Well, you couldn't do those things before. So,
you had no choice but to go to the core, and if
by any chance the download and upload time prevents
the app from having a 100% score there in
Lighthouse. For example, in our case
as users and developers of apps, we can always
achieve a hybrid rendering mechanism
in Angular, right? And this SSR that started
with 17, if I remember correctly,
with 16 I think they incorporated some experimental things,
is basically stable in the
framework for a few versions now.
They keep incorporating capabilities there.
Analog directly benefits from that as a
metaframework, but I also know many
people who develop apps with server-side rendering using the
Angular engine. And now for 22 they add,
as you already saw in the changelog,
the ability to do component resource caching, supporting
synchronous values in stream-based resources.
I have a question. If you were starting an app
from scratch, would you use SSR by default?
I think I would. Good, that's what I wanted.
It depends, of course, it always depends,
right? If it's a very tiny application that won't
have almost any impact. But if I'm going
to start an app that will scale to, let's say, a project of
dimensions we don't know
yet and you know there is a unique value there in the app for it to have
a luxury performance, a performance that is
aligned with modern expectations,
I wouldn't do without everything related to
server-side rendering.
I would use it from scratch by creating the project
with the CLI from the beginning. Yes, SSR. Totally. Yes,
yes, use whatever architecture you want on the
server side, but give it the opportunity with
all this incremental hydration, also with deferrable views,
for the app to give its best, because
there will always be extra kilobytes that you never took
into account that will impact the performance of the app.
Therefore, you try to aim for 100% to be able
to have
95, 97 in the Lighthouse score. And of course,
not only when measuring a metric
synthetically in a lab with these
computers we use, but so that
any user, regardless of the type
of device or connection capacity they have on the network,
can load the page quickly and not have to be
exposed to underlying problems of rendering
the full page. Even more so pages that
have gigantic component trees,
that have a forest of components, a couple
of component trees, and if you delegate all of that
to the browser in Client-side Rendering, it won't
work the same way. Okay, we think
the same. For me it is already almost a default—I mean,
if you know that, again, if it's a test
you won't use it, but if you know it's one that will
scale or the goal is for it to scale, why
not start from scratch with SSR directly?
Exactly. And now as of 22, for example,
incremental hydration is enabled by
default in platform-browser, which
means that it will directly improve,
it will positively impact the Core Web Vitals in
server-side rendering applications by preventing it
from destroying, doing all that destructive hydration
of the DOM, and it will do nothing other
than boost the performance of the apps
you build. For me SSR is no longer
a must, right? It becomes almost a default.
Likewise. And closing, how about we take a
look at what's new in tooling in 22?
It's the nice part. I mean, I think this is
what everyone looks at first.
Let's be honest, right? The tooling in DevTools,
which is the Angular tooling that always—
hey, is there something new in Angular DevTools,
is there something new with the MCPs? And well,
now with this provider function of
provideAngularMCPTools, which is nothing more than
a wrapper of the experimental function. Careful, all of
this is not stable, other things are stable,
but not this MCP specifically yet.
And what that wrapper does is allow defining,
or rather declaring Angular MCP tools
directly in a provider instead of
letting the MCP and everyone waste tokens
trying to find the execution context.
It's like with MCPs everything becomes nice,
to be honest. It's like, I don't know what else to say, I mean,
it's like we have support, we have compatibility,
we have everything set up. What is missing not to
have fun? No, I mean, very nerd of me,
maybe waiting for the toolings, I don't know,
but for me the fun is right there,
I mean, commodity versus fun. This is what
gives me the fun. I don't know if
you think the same, but for me
it's very interesting to see how one can... Remember
the joy that Firebug with Firefox gave us
20 years ago when you could see how
everything was working granularly
on a website at that time. If you have
that toy on your side,
which is even a toy that allows you to speed up
understanding the system behind it,
obviously that is super welcome. Yes.
And here I make a callout to people, yes,
to learn, I mean, not to just get carried away
by what the system does or what the
MCP gives you or whatever. Challenge yourself
by asking the AI if it is right,
if it is not right or what could be improved or not,
because this gives us a lot of things,
right? Well, they give us everything, basically
served on a silver platter for us to improve. The point
is whether we improve or not. So here
the idea of having fun is with that. You have everything
to play with and everything to learn. So it's about
taking advantage, right? And learning that way. It's like
before you had to go to a YouTube video, you had
to go to a course, you had to sit for 1000 hours.
Now you can while you are shipping, right?,
since now everyone is like a shipper, while
you are creating, while you are shipping, you can
learn, right? And I think there is an advantage
between the people who learn and want to
really grow compared to those who just
go to complete—which is fine, mind you, I don't
say it's bad, but I think you see the
differences, right? Just like before when whoever cared
more about performance, this, that,
did more things. Nowadays I think whoever
understands architecture best, how tools work,
and everything, will be the person who goes
the furthest, so to speak, right? Exactly. And also
let's not forget the compiler CLI which allows
doing all the compilation using, well,
ESBuild along with Vite nowadays for development
environments, now with 22 it receives official
support and full compatibility with Node 26, which
will be, by the way, as we've known for
a few months, the last of the traditional
release scheme where even numbers
were LTS and odd numbers were experimental. Node.js,
we are not talking about Angular as such.
And well, starting with Node 27, which will be released
next year, because the Node release cycle
will be annual, all versions will
be Long Term Support, that is, support for
the long term. I think the support they give is
about 2 years or something like that. So it will be
a framework task to keep updated every
year with Node.js in a much less convoluted
and complicated way, not only for us, but
for themselves to have to be on top of
what appeared with a new even version
that was in LTS. For me everyone, everyone,
when I say everyone I mean everyone, sooner or later they
will go to a model like that because it reaches a point
of maturity, right? Before we took longer for everything and
again I say that. So I think it reaches a
point of maturity unless, I don't know, tomorrow some
Chrome-like thing comes along and changes everything, right? But if not,
which I don't think will happen, but it could also happen or not
in Chrome, but yes in all this way in which
things move super fast. Maybe the Angular roadmap
suddenly incorporates something that none of
us had seen or took time to see and it may
allow one to continue being someone who
is evolving along with the industry
instead of staying in a corner of a sofa like perhaps
it might have looked in another era or in other
roles. Clean. Yes. Or like what happened to Node in its
time, never reaching version one and suddenly
going to version 16, right? When they merged
with io.js. But what I see is that everyone will go
to stability, many security patches,
many patches with small features, but minor
releases we're talking about, right? The majors
for me are going to be a bit longer. You can't
keep majors every 6 months if there are no breaking
changes. And as we discussed about a
month ago back at Google Cloud Next, it's very difficult
to have to convince the business of this whole
fast-paced cycle. That's where things might go in the
future. What we use will have that stable
label and won't constantly go through this
fast-paced 6-month cycle, sometimes even
less in the case of other types of systems,
and one has more time to land things well and
be able to modernize code in a much more
efficient way in the long run. I think that in fact even
the browser itself is more stable today. So,
the browser is stable, V8 is stable, right?
So, we start with all the stabilities
that are like a domino, the chips are falling.
What frameworks lack is
updating silently as happens in the
case of Evergreen Browsers, so you don't
have to be on top of that or run any specific
command to perform the update,
or downloading the .exe file or looking for it
again on the website for the new version,
but letting it do it on its own, auto-cleaning.
An auto-cleaning CLI wouldn't be bad, huh?
Yes, yes, that is probably... it's risky,
of course, because you are not going to let
your cleanup kill elements that you don't
yet have on your project roadmap, but yes
anyone can easily implement
that. So Jorge, thank you very much
again for being here, and let's hope in a
couple of days to see what the developer event brings, and
hopefully in one of the GDGs or in one of the
environments of the spaces that will be created
we can meet. Totally. Thank you very much
again. Greetings to everyone for making it this far
and we'll see if they come with some surprise. As far as
I know there is none, but I like creating hype.
Let's see what comes out in the Developer Preview
video and we'll watch it.